foreign
live stream 52.2 on March 9th 2023.
welcome to the octave Institute we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
you can find more information on these
links
this is a recorded and archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
head over to activeinference.org to
learn more about getting involved with
projects and learning groups
all right
we are back
in live stream 52.2
in our third discussion on the paper
geometric methods for sampling
optimization inference and adaptive
agents
we had a zero background and context
video
and last week Lance joined for 52.1
where we had a great overview discussion
on the paper
So today we're going to see where it
goes see where
our last week has taken us and how we're
thinking about it or curious about it if
you're watching live of course feel free
to write questions in a live chat
otherwise let us pick up on a mostly
blank slide
and uh
just thanks again Lance for joining if
you want to give
any sort of
introduction or recap opening here go
for it
well yeah I mean thanks a lot Daniel for
organizing this I'm super happy to be
here
um I think well last time we went
through most of the paper
uh we discussed a lot about sampling I
guess the idea of sampling we discussed
a bit less about hamiltonian Monte Carlo
which is one of the I guess
state-of-the-art methods for sampling in
continuous space
um we discussed a lot about optimization
there's a nice figure actually that we
can discuss today which is which gives
some nice intuition about the kind of
optimization methods that we reviewed in
the paper
um and then there's another section on
statistical inference so this is a bit
of a different section that uh than
people in the free energy principle
literature and active influence are used
to because here the goal of inference
is about approximating expectations
as opposed to just approximating
distributions in and of themselves it
turns out to be
these two perspectives turn out to be
dual but I guess here we want to develop
Notions of divergences and discrepancies
that are a bit more General than the KL
Divergence and that can use to solve
problems that the kale Divergence cannot
um and I guess the overall picture for
what we want to do that is
the kale Divergence turns out to have a
lot of really nice properties
that we can discuss one of them is that
if the Cal Divergence is reduced it
means that that the two distributions in
play
um are more similar in terms of
information so there is this idea of
information well not monotonicity
whether KL Divergence sort of
um yeah gives an ordering as to what
extent to this two distributions
quantify I mean so if you had three
distributions and you compute the KL
Divergence between them
um and now KL of Av is
lower than KL of AC it means that b
um is more closer in terms of
information to a than C is to a so you
have this really nice thing that is
captured by local Divergence with which
makes sense when we're dealing with
information the kale Divergence also has
some many other nice properties
um
it it's not a distance but it turns out
to behave a bit like a square distance
so you have this kind of like really
nice Pythagorean theorem
um and I won't get into the exact
statement but it's like if you have uh a
b and c distributions then klab plus
klac equals klbc if you have like a
rectangle triangle if a b c Define a
rectangle triangle in information space
um you have other properties regular KL
Deliverance gives and so on
um civical evidence is in general I
would say the distribution the
Divergence of choice but it turns out
that in many cases you just can't use it
for example when you have samples and
you want to approximate some samples
with a distribution then the Cal
leverage just is not going to vary back
so you need to derive some other things
so this is to say that we're considering
statistical inference a bit more
generally than what we do in active
inference in general
and so this speaks to why the
distraction here is a bit different from
the standard inference literature that
that we usually consider and then I
think that the well then the section 5
which is about active inference and I
think we should discuss that a little
bit more because the formation of active
inference that's presented there is to
my mind the most General and also the
simplest concept conceptually that's
been out there I mean we sort of like
recap the derivation of active inference
and also like the properties of the
expected free energy properties of
active inference and also how to scale
active inference and so on and we do
that in just seven pages or five or five
pages I mean it's just very short
um so it stands sure
bits like a really concise memory and
actually from there you can rederive a
lot of you know technical papers on
active inference it's like to me it's
the most General and
if if you as a reader can understand
that section then you can sort of really
understand what active reference is
about
um so yeah this is kind of the overview
for today
um I would really like to be discussing
questions because last time we
rediscussed about most of the papers so
but yeah whatever comes up
awesome
all right great well let us uh
talk about some of the more
foundational pieces
hamiltonian Monte Carlo and then on
through section four
with the points that you raised about
the KL
which generalized inference Beyond how
it may have been brought up in other
active and then we can spend most of the
time in section five and looking at some
of those figures connecting some of the
intuitions about the ball rolling down
the bowl
to the person running
so sounds good on hamiltonian Monte
Carlo where do you want to pick up
sure I mean so hamiltonian so last time
we discussed a lot about the problem of
sampling and why that's a difficult
problem
um
and we arrived at the conclusion or or
it presented like Monte Carlo methods
how they work so you're basically
running a stochastic process like a
random random motion and sort of the
distribution defining the process is
going to convert their target
distribution which means that when you
run the process long enough
then every point that it's gonna be in
is going to be like a sample of the
distribution that you want to sample
from
um now there's a lot of issues with that
um I mean conceptually it's not so
difficult but actually when you want to
implement this in practice it turns out
to be really hard because
if you just implement this simplest
stochastic process to assemble your
target distribution
um it's going to be extremely slow and I
think that's the main bottleneck When
developing Monte Carlo methods Monte
Carlo something and in general is slow
and that's also one of the reason one of
the reasons why one might want to do
variational inference instead of
sampling
um so something is slower but it's also
more accurate it can approximate our
distributions that are completely
arbitrary so if you care about accuracy
then and you have time and computational
resources then for sure go for sampling
if you care about speed about doing
things online and you don't care about
accuracy so much then the right annoying
prints is the way to go at least that's
my understanding right now
so
let's say you wanted to sample a
distribution in a continuous space so it
could be
um just as last time let's imagine the
state space is the desk where where I'm
at and you sort of had this this
distribution which could be like
multimodo very weird and you just want
to take samples from there
um Monte Carlo is probably the state of
the art methods method to do that
there's a lot of other methods out there
but San Antonio Monte Carlo typically it
just works very well and in a wide
variety of situations
until the area of hamiltonian Monte
Carlo is you're gonna augment
the state space with
um so let let's say that the original
state space you start with are the
positions
and so you're gonna augment that with a
velocity State space so you kind of if
your original state space was euclidean
space of n Dimensions you just end up
with a new cleanest place of two n
Dimensions so you double the size of the
state space
and then you say okay well
um the distribution that I want to
sample from actually defines an energy
landscape
um so it technically technically it's
like if you take if you have
distribution which is p then minus log p
is an energy landscape so
um points where minus log p is low are
points where p is high and so these are
points that you want to sample a lot
from
and control wise
um if minus log T is very high then p is
low and you don't really want to go
there so much because these are points
of low probability
so I think this minus log P actually
there's many reasons why minus log p is
is Meaningful in physics but just note
for now that minus log p is just like a
function and the Minima of the functions
of that function have the high
probability point and
is there high these are high energy
points where
you basically don't want to go to go
there so much
um so let's pull this minus log P
potential energy and so this is what
this really is in physics if the
technically in physics P would be give
us a measure what people call an
equilibrium distribution
um
last time we saw like soft Max of minus
something the something is the is the
potential energy
um anyway and so
minus log P would be the potential
energy
and then if you if you add kinetic
energy on your velocities
um then you get what's called a
hamiltonian which is the sum of the
potential and kinetic energies so
what is exactly the kinetic energy the
kinetic energy is like velocity squared
pretty much uh so if you had
remember that your state space is
position and velocity if you add and you
take a point in state space the
uh so you would have
um kinetic energy which is velocity
squared and the potential energy which
would be minus log Peak now if you add
the two together what you get is a
hamiltonian which is the sum of the
kinetic energy and potential energy and
this is just standard physics
hamiltonian is a sum of kinetic and
potential energy and it gives us a total
energy of the system
um so why
we started with the problem of sampling
and here I just told you something very
complicated where we get a hamiltonian
there's actually a good reason why we
want to do that and it comes back to the
idea of geometric integration that we
talked about last time
which is that
um typically
maybe I have a process that I know would
will give very efficient sampling but
actually when I implement it on a
computer in discrete time I just lose
all the all the properties that make
that something efficient so actually it
turns out that most people working in
Monte Carlo sampling they're working on
efficient discretizations of continuous
processes as opposed to on the
continuous processes themselves really
the bottleneck and the difficulty here
is is the implementation part
implementing process on on a computer
like you and I had
in such a way that we retain all the
good sampling properties
so one very powerful idea is that of
geometric integration which is of
preserving geometric properties of a
system I mean geometric integration is
the field that develops computational
methods of numerical integration and
numerical discretization in such a way
that they preserve important geometric
properties of the system
here in the gym the geometry in play is
the hamiltonian and so you might think
well that's pretty weird I mean a
hamiltonian is an energy and here we're
talking about preserving the geometry
and preserving The hamiltonian Howdy
these two things fit together and so it
turns out that
the presence of a hamiltonian and the
fact that we have a state space that has
positions and velocity
um technically in mathematics what what
we then get is what people called
emblematic geometry so symbolic geometry
is just arises when we had those State
space that comprise positions and
velocity and when where you have
hamiltonians
so this is just like a way of explaining
why the hamiltonian why the hamiltonian
is like closely and intimately related
to Geometry
so geometric integration enables you to
um to yeah to disco type processes in
such a way that the hamiltonian is
preserved now when you think about the
hamiltonian the hamiltonian gives you
the energy of a particular point in
state space
and so
if you simulate trajectories that
preserve the hamiltonian
what you're effectively doing is
sampling from The Contours of the
probability distribution Contours that
have the same probability
so you're basically going around let's
say
for example in circles
in a region that has the same
probability
when we want to sample we we want to go
everywhere I mean we want to sample
regions of high probability low
probability and want to be able to go
from one to the other
so what geometric integration allows us
to do
is to simulate dynamics that are going
to preserve the Contours of the
probability distribution and are going
to do so very well
um the advantage here is that when we
use geometric integration to simulate
hamiltonian Dynamics which are
conservative and again stay in the
Contours
what geometric integration allows us to
do is to take time steps that are very
long so it enables us to travel very far
in the landscape while still preserving
the hamiltonian so you don't need to
take very small time steps to remain
accurate
and present the hamiltonian but actually
geometric integration allows you to you
know take very long time steps and still
preserve the hamiltonian
so
now we have a dynamic that simultaneous
preserving that's just very good because
you can take very long time steps and
that enables you to go around the
Contours of the probability distribution
so what you want to do next is you know
to change Contours you want to go to
Contours that are of higher probability
Contours of lower probability and you
want to do so in a way that the Contours
of high probability are sampled much
more and much more often than the
Contours of lower probability
um so what you do is that you augment
your hamiltonian Dynamic with what
people call a velocity refreshment or a
momentum refreshment
and so this is how I work how it works
um so you're gonna yeah simulate your
hamiltonian Dynamics for for some time
and then after after a while you're
gonna be like okay well now I'm gonna
I'm gonna change the velocity at random
by by just drawing a new velocity from a
gaussian distribution
and so by drawing
a new velocity from a gaussian
distribution you're just going to change
Contour completely
and then this what's called
um and and then there's the constraint I
just talked about which is you want to
change Contours of the probability
distribution in such a way that Contours
of high probability are visited much
more often than Contours of low
probability so you want to preserve that
you want to do that
um proportionately in a way
so
the third ingredient of hamiltonian
Monte Carlo comes in which is a
metropolis Hastings
and some Metropolis Hastings is this
accept rejects that that we discussed
briefly last time and so Metropolis
testing is just super clever
and it enables you to to say
um to it just tells you whether this
um
this momentum refreshing step is
actually a good one or a bad one and
should be redacted
a mountain refreshment is good if
overall your sampling is gonna remain
um is gonna remain faithful to the
Target distribution but it is bad if it
remains Unfaithful so actually
running this Metropolis state things
except rejects that allows you to
change Contours of the probability
distribution in a way that remains
faithful to the Target distribution and
so there you go that that's basically
hamiltonian Monte Carlo so to recap
you augment the state Space by adding
velocities
this allows you to
build the hamiltonian by declaring that
the original probability distribution
gives you a potential energy and you add
a kinetic energy on the on the
velocities
um which is just velocity squared
because you have a hamiltonian you can
you can use geometric integration to
simulate hamiltonian Dynamics very
accurately and with very long time steps
the random time steps is a crucial thing
because it means avoid very low
computational cost you can sample very
far so it means that you don't get stuck
in a region of the probability
distribution where you can actually
visit it
much more fast and efficiently
so that's the first part
um the problem with those Dynamics again
is that they remain on the Contour of
the probability distribution and so you
want to sample the whole probability
distribution so what you do is every
once in a while and I think that's a
hyper parameter in your in your sampling
algorithm let's say every 10 iterations
of the hamiltonian dynamic every 10 time
steps of the hamiltonian dynamic you're
going to sample
um you're just gonna randomly take a new
velocity So you you're gonna change
Contour in the probability distribution
and The crucial point there is you want
to change Contour in a way that's
faithful of the probability distribution
and that's faithful the sampling problem
that you want to do
there comes the last thing which is
Metropolis Hastings which ensures that
the momentum refreshment will be uh good
for sampling I mean we'll preserve your
target probability distribution
so with that
you just get a very efficient
um sampling algorithm and so it seems a
bit convoluted right the
um one bottleneck of course is that you
need to double the dimension of the
state space
and if your database is already
extremely large that could be a
bottleneck it could be the case that I
actually doubling the dimension to add
velocities it could be a computational
bottleneck so that's a problem
um but still in most cases that not a
problem
and um
so again hamiltonian Monte Carlo is
convoluted but the overall take-home
message I would want you to to take from
this is that it is a method that remains
faithful to the probability distribution
they want to sample and this is crucial
and it is also a method that through
geometric integration it enables you to
take time steps that are very long and
still get accurate sampling
so this is the the really cool thing
um if you you could come up with a whole
bunch of other methods that did not
require to you know double the dimension
of the state space or that didn't use
geometric integration so the problem
that you would probably run into is that
the
over the the thing that you came up with
when you implement it in the computer it
doesn't exactly preserve the the
probability distribution that you want
to sample
and so the problem with that is that
this would lead to biased sampling and
by assembling by assembling is like
you're gonna sample a different
probability distribution which might be
just a bit different but still
um a different probability distribution
than what you really want to sample and
this would bias your your predictions so
the really cool thing of hamiltonian
Monte Carlo is that you're actually able
to have unbiased sampling through the
Metropolis Hastings step
um and this is a crucial thing so it's
computationally implementable in general
there's no computational bottlenecks
apart from this doubling of State space
and it leads to unbiased sampling and
it's also relatively simple so this is
why this is really used all over the
place
there's um there's another few
perspectives that might explain why it
works so well
so in in the paper in in section
in the last subsection of of uh of
section two which is about optimization
um so the the section on optimization is
about how to accelerate optimization how
to derive an optimization algorithm
um yeah yeah 2.6 yeah that's the one so
the whole thing about section two
is about deriving an optimization
algorithm that accelerated in a physical
way and by immune accelerate what I mean
by accelerated it's not about just going
faster but it's about having
acceleration
um and which means that so if you go
slightly up in the paper on the figure
I think this figure is great and by the
way I wasn't the one who who came up
with this figure but I think I think
this figure is great it really gives a
lot of intuition for what acceleration
really is
so if you
if you look at the at the green cup I
don't know how you call this uh the
green well on the left
uh this would be like um a ball rolling
down a little while in like uh and the
well is filled up honey to to like a
certain level and so there you get a lot
of friction so your ball would just roll
down very very slowly
and the speed of the bow will be
proportionate to the slope of the well
um so this is not accelerated because
there's a lot of friction and so the
speed is just proportional to the slope
of the well and this so This is actually
what grade in the sun does
but now if you go on the right you get
what people call in physics on
understand system which is also an
accelerated system a system that's
meaningfully accelerated so if you
replace the honey
uh in the world by some water then
there's going to be way less friction
and your bow is actually going to
accelerate and overshoot the minimum of
the well and then sort of stabilize but
the point here is that this um
this bow is just gonna get so much
faster to the minimum
now
um so let's say that we just
um I mean so this optimization this idea
for optimization is is just extremely
powerful and um and by the way on the
right hand side in the graph you can see
the improvements that you get when you
when you implement these sort of ideas
so this was on I'll come back to to
sampling in a bit I promise but this is
actually very well very related
um you you can see on the graph on the
right what kind of improvements you get
when you go from a under
the first order system grade in the send
system to a well good when you go from
an overdamped first order creating the
Sun System to an underdamp second order
accelerated system and so you can see
the curve right um
so the Black slash orange curve is
overdone there's no acceleration it's
very slow
um the the last curve the the blue one
it's accelerated and it's just super
fast so you can see it sort of gives you
like a quantitative data as to how many
improvements you can get by implementing
this acceleration in a physically
meaningful way
could you just describe the axes of the
graph and also what the lead group is
here
um so the Lee group is um so in in the
figure legend in the fourth line you see
the E group is son so that's this um
technically that the special or
orthogonal group of Dimensions n and so
if I if I remember correctly these are
all the matrices all the square matrices
of size n by n that have a determinant
equal to one so the determinant is just
like um
a function where you give it a matrix
and it gives you a number
the fact that
um the fact that the determinant is
equal to one means that here we're just
taking matrices which are um which
produce Trend not translations but
changes of coordinates that preserve the
geometry in a system
so so just to to elaborate on this a
little bit because
for people who are not intimately
familiar with Matrix is it might be a
little opaque
um so when you have a matrix
a matrix can multiply vectors so a
square Matrix takes in a vectors of size
of Dimension n and it outputs vectors of
Dimension and by multiplication
so if you have a square Matrix
it just induces a transformation of your
state space because each each Vector
each point which is the vector gets
converted into another point which is
another vector
now
um
the so there's a lot of I guess
properties there right you could have
all sorts of translations of State space
or rotations in state space or
transformations of database if the
determinant of the Matrix is equal to
one
it means that the transformation of
State space that the Matrix
induces uh will preserve the geometry of
the six facial preserve distances
if you and it will preserve crucially
orientation as well because if the if
you only asked
um the determinant to be equal to one or
minus one then you would the The Matrix
transformation would preserve the
geometry but it would not preserve the
orientation it could like mirror things
um so if you only asked the determinant
to be equal to one or minus one you
would get a Lee group that's called the
orthogonal group which is usually
denoted o of N and here we we require
the
determinant to be just equal to one and
so you get the special or orthogonal
group and so it's this group of matrices
that have this property now this is not
um really I mean this is not really
important for the example here because
you could have taken any other lead
group and got something similar and got
a similar difference in performance
but but um
yeah I guess it's just interesting for
its own sake
um and so the graph though the K is the
number of iterations so the number of
time steps so that's the x-axis
and the um the y-axis is how close you
are from the minimum
and and it's in lock scale so as you can
see the the blue curve is gonna get like
in 100 iterations it's going to get
basically at 10 to the minus 4 10 to the
minus 5 distance from the minimum so
it's like super super close it's
basically gets there in 100 iterations
uh when you take the other normal
gradient descent methods where you see
that it's going to take so much longer
um
so yeah this is really the advantage of
using second order method and what I
mean by second order method is that
by second order means that you actually
doubled the state space to introduce
velocities so that you not only have a
dynamical system over positions where
you have a dynamical system of
velocities and so it means that you have
a physically
um a physical notion of acceleration
because acceleration is a movement of
velocities
um and so if you double this database by
saying this is position this is
velocities and you say I have a motion
in this like a state space that's twice
as big then you have a meaningfully a
meaningful notion of acceleration
uh and this is really powerful and so
you can see already a parallel here
which is that hamiltonian Monte Carlo
also has this notion of acceleration in
some way uh at least just intuitively
because we we also uh doubled the size
of the state space to introduce
velocities
and so it turns out that this situation
is actually uh you can make it into a
formal correspondence
um and this is I think this is something
that quite interests me to be honest
um so if you if you remember if we come
back to the intuition for sampling the
intuition for sampling through Monte
Carlo methods is we have a target
distribution that we want to sample from
so we're gonna run a dynamic random
Dynamic towards that towards that
distribution now what makes sampling
efficient is that the distribution that
characterizes the process because again
the process is random so that each time
it is at the random location that is
characterized by a distribution what
makes sampling efficient is that the
distribution characterizing in the
process just converges as fast as
possible to think that you want to
sample from so there is
this is to say that you can think of
sampling as an optimization on the space
of probability distributions you want to
move your probability distribution of
the process as fast as possible to your
target
and so you can see from there that
sampling is actually not so different
from variational inference
um
it's just the same idea only variational
inference you're typically gonna like
um yeah take a parameterized family of
distributions and approximate the target
while here you have a non-parametrized
family that's given by your Dynamic
that's going to perfectly match the
target
um
so so again so
so with that I want you to have the take
home message that sampling you can think
about it as an optimization on the space
operability distributions in the sense
that you have a target distribution and
you want to get there as fast as you can
with a process
now
let's suppose and so here is the crucial
connection between sampling and
optimization in in the way that we've
described it here
let's suppose that you run this
accelerated optimization scheme on the
space of probability distributions
then the the process so you would get
the dynamic on the space of the
probability distributions that has a
meaningful notion of acceleration
through through the accelerated method
that that was shown here
so if you look at what that what kind of
dynamic this really gives you
it gives you a process which is given by
a stochastic differential equation that
is known as under that logical Dynamics
um so there's an equation for it in I
think a section subsection 2.8 but the
point is under larger Dynamics is a
stochastic differential equation
whose density or probability
distribution
those this accelerated optimization
problem on the space of permitted
distributions
so just from there you know that
underground Dynamics is going to be a
very efficient sampler because it
meaningfully accelerates and gets the
target
I mean quite fast
the problem is
Dynamics you cannot simulate it
accurately or you can simulate that
accurately but you cannot simulate it
exactly on your computer in practice so
this comes back to the numerical
integration problem that we discussed
just before
um
and so you have to to find a way to to
discretize or or in other words
Implement underground Dynamics on your
computer in such a way that you retain
that the thing that you implemented on
the computer retains this meaningful
notion of acceleration
and so it turns out that you can see
a hamiltonian Monte Carlo as a faithful
numerical discretization or numerical
implementation of under that logical
Dynamics that's going to preserve these
acceleration properties and therefore
these this efficient sampling
so this is all like
um yeah a lot of interesting connections
but basically what I want to get at is
you really have this notion of
acceleration that permeates
where I guess physics but here it
permeates sampling and it permeates
optimization and so the method that was
shown here about optimization and
hamiltonian Monte Carlo they're just the
same in a way only one is applied to
optimization the other is applied to
optimization on probability
distributions of AKA sampling
great I guess last question on this part
what is the Shadow hamiltonian and why
does it sound so cool
I know right yeah it's uh it's really
cool
um and it's a recall name so the shadow
hamiltonian is
um okay so so let's go back to the
hamiltonian
so we have a hamiltonian and we want to
simulate the dynamic that preserved the
hamiltonian we want to implement that on
the computer we're going to do that
through geometric integration
geometric grid integration gives you a
bunch of algorithms to preserve the
hamiltonian I mean a bunch of algorithms
they can Implement on the computer and
they're going to preserve the
hamiltonian
do they actually really preserve the
hamiltonian it turns out that no so what
uh what I said before is a bit of a
shortcut like
um
because the numerical integration or
that you get through
any any numerical method including
geometric integration is not going to
exactly preserve the hamiltonian but
it's gonna preserve what people call a
shadow Hamilton which is
almost the same as the hamiltonian but
with extra terms that sort of vanish if
the if the time step is very is very
short
um
so
this is to say that your numerical
Dynamic uh implemented through geometric
integration is gonna exactly preserve
the Shadow hamiltonian and approximately
preserve the true hamiltonian and so
there is um in the paper we show
um I don't know if it's well it's
probably algorithm dependent but
basically depending on the algorithm
that you choose you want to show to what
extent the shadow hamiltonian truly
approximates the true hamiltonian the
the virtue of geometric integration
methods is that actually the shadow
hamiltonian turns out to be extremely
close to True hamiltonian which means
that you can take a very long time steps
and still be very good at approx at
preserving the true hamiltonian so here
you don't
when you implement these methods you
don't exactly preserve the true
hamiltonian but you do you still do it
pretty well and so in hamiltonian Monte
Carlo
um the
momentum refreshment and Metropolis
brutally the Metropolis Hastings accept
rejects them it is gonna correct
for those failures
of of truly uh preserving the
hamiltonian so even though you have some
you don't you don't exactly preserve the
hamiltonian in your numerical
integration in hamiltonian Monte Carlo
the Metropolis Hastings accept reject
step is gonna correct for this
inaccuracy and so this is like really
the true beauty of hamiltonian Monte
Carlo
is that even though you get a lot of
things that are not exactly preserved
when you implement things on a computer
thanks to Metropolis Hastings
overall your sampling is gonna be
perfect in the sense that you're going
to truly preserve your target
distribution so this is really the key
um now a follow-up question to that is
okay well if Metropolis Hastings it's
just so crucial and it just gives your
Dynamic
um
the property that it's gonna preserve
whatever it does even if it samples
really badly issue and Metropolis
Hastings it's still gonna
um preserve your target distribution
then why can't you just come up with the
average process like whatever kind of
process another Metropolis Hastings at
the end
and so you can do that you can take any
kind of process
and
after and
so let's say you take a random process
it could be the worst in the world let's
say you wanted to sample from a gaussian
and you actually take a Brownian motion
now this is clearly now going to work
because brand new motion just goes all
over the place it could go infinitely
far ground emotion and it's just like
random motion right completely random
motion no there is structure to it but
there's no the structure in brown
emotion means that is touch that
Browning motion is just gonna just
spread really really far so Browning
motion is not going to preserve your
target distribution
so it's gonna and it's also going to be
very slow by the way so it's not gonna
be a good sampler
if you add Metropolis Hastings on Brown
emotion which is
you integrate by emotion so you just
simulate a step of running motion on the
computer and then you you do Metropolis
Hastings to to know whether you should
accept or reject that step which obvious
Hastings will tell you whether you
should do it or not you either accept
and you stay and you keep going from
that new position or you reject and you
start from where you started from and
take a new sample accept reject if you
accept you keep going if you reject you
go back and you sort of go like that so
if you do Metropolis testing there your
standard is going to be exact so it is
going to preserve the Target and so
you're gonna have accurate sampling
um and so this is crucial this really
highlights the importance of metropolis
Hastings but and there is a big but your
your sampler here is going to be
extremely slow and it's going to be
extremely slow first of all because
brand emotion in and of itself it
doesn't at all preserve the target
distribution I mean just goes all over
the place and you just wanna
sample a lot around the mood of the
gaussian for example
so it means that Metropolis Hasting will
reject a lot of your steps because a
little of your steps will try to go
further away by you while you want to
stay around the mode typically of the
gaussian
so you're gonna do a lot of steps for
nothing
and also run in motion just does not
have the qualities that make a sampler
efficient
and so the the reason why hamiltonian
Monte Carlo is so good is because it's
able to integrate Metropolis Hastings
and still preserve a lot of other
properties that make
um
that that make the sampler efficient
so
if we remember
Tony Monte Carlo has this geometric
integration that does not exactly
preserve the hamiltonian but
it does still does it pretty well
approximately by preserving a shadow
hamiltonian so this means already that
in that integration step is going to be
really good so there's going to be a lot
of accept acceptance
in the Metropolis Hastings
um
so so and and also the way the way the
scheme is set up there's going to be a
lot of acceptance step in the Metropolis
Hastings so it means that most of the
samples that you would draw will
actually be used instead of being
rejected and you have to start over
again so that's one advantage
the other the other advantage of
Hamilton in Monte Carlo and this is a
crucial one and we kind of discussed
this last week
is that one crucial thing to be a good
sampler is this idea of time
irreversibility
and so I'll emphasize it again because
it's really crucial and there's a lot of
literature on this and it's something
that we reviewed also in the paper
so a sampler that is time reversible
even if that is time irreversible
is always going to be
better or it's at least not going to be
worse than than a sampler that is time
reversible so what do we mean by this
a sample is time irreversible
um if and only if
uh were you to play the Dynamics forward
or backward there will be
um yeah so
yeah so so going on your bullet point
here a sample is time reversible if and
on the ETF if you were to play the
Dynamics forward or backward in time so
forward in time and then maybe you would
play them by reversing the movie
um by playing the movie backwards
uh if you were to do that then
um
then the the two movies that you would
see would be qualitatively the same and
statistically the same
so the process is time reversible if and
only if the process if you're running
forward or backward it's basically
statistically the same now what does
this mean in practice well
if your process is time reversible then
it's going to backtrack very often
actually
um so it means that you you would be
somewhere uh in the probability
distribution just sampling there and you
will go forward and then you probably go
backward and so on and you kind of get
stuck in a region until you go somewhere
else but it's just going to be very slow
to move around
um and so it's going to be very slow to
get uh you know good sampling because
it's going to take you a long time to
visit all the regions of the probability
distribution in other words the
distribution characterizing the process
it's not it's going to move very slowly
to the Target distribution that's
another way to look at it
um
if the process is time irreversible on
the other hand then it's a lot less
likely to go backward during the
sampling process so it means that it's
going to visit the target distribution a
lot more I mean it's just going to go
around imagine if you're not allowed to
go backward just as a human being and
you're walking around you're gonna just
gonna end up in many more places than if
you were allowed to go backward and if
you were and if you were just going
backward all the time to where you
started then you wouldn't
be able to to do a lot of visiting so it
would be a bad temper
so so I guess there's some like a
straightforward in intuition there
um so one idea is in sampling is we want
to optimize the extent to which
um a sampler is timely reversible we
want to increase time and reversibility
as much as we can to force December to
just move around as much as possible
so that's an idea and and it is explored
currently I guess it's a bit of an open
problem of how how do you really do that
and how do you implement that on a
computer in a way that you know works
and preserves all the properties
um but the point I want to I wanted to
get to is that
um Metropolis Hastings is a blessing and
it also a curse it is a blessing because
when you add it to any kind of process
you will make your sampling unbiased so
it means that you will
sample the right distribution even
though you're implementing this on a
computer and there can be a lot of so
many issues with the numerically
numerical integration numerical
approximation and so on
but it's also a curse because whenever
you add Metropolis Hastings
um on on the process it's going to make
it time reversible
[Music]
so actually
yeah if you if you just took a random
process and added metropoly six things
you would get something that's
inevitably going to be quite low
and so now you get to the you know the
problem or the conundrum where what do I
do
um do I go for unbiased sampling do I
care about accuracy
um and then I should add a metropolis
Hastings or do I not care about accuracy
so much
um and then I should not have Metropolis
space Hastings and it's going to go
faster generally
um
and so hamiltonian Monte Carlo actually
has the blessing and does not have the
curse and this is why hamiltonian Monte
Carlo is just so good
and again it's also complementary to all
of the things
that we've been discussing and the
reason why hamiltonian Monte Carlo is
blessed and not cursed is because the
momentum the
how do you call this the Metropolis
Hastings is just done on the momentum
refreshment step as opposed to being
done on the overall dynamic
so because if you remember you do
geometric integration to simulate
hamiltonian Dynamics and then every once
in a while you will take a momentum
refreshment and then do Metropolis
Hastings on that momentum refreshment as
opposed to doing Metropolis Hastings on
both the hamiltonian dynamic and the
momentum refreshment
so it's it's not
um it's not something that I can really
explain how how that works but it turns
out that by just doing the Metropolis I
mean Monte Carlo is a way of having
Metropolis Hastings in a way that you
preserve the unbiasedness that's so that
your sampling is accurate but you don't
sacrifice the time irreversibility and
so and so you get both
um
less and this is because the Metropolis
hitting is just one of the components
and not on both
to kind of connect that to an example as
we move into active inference
here we have some probability ISO
Contours some we have the high
probability carpool lane and then we
have some lower probability Lanes
and uh we can go different speeds in
these lanes and we want to have a full
accelerated
model here
it's almost like the MH is is refreshing
our velocity just asking when we want to
change the lanes but it's not our full
self-driving car
Metropolis Hastings algorithm but we're
able to use our position and
acceleration when we're in our Lane
to take full advantage of the
acceleration following the shadow Road
not necessarily the true road but the
shadow road is close enough or the
Shadows on the road and then
Lane changes are these computationally
costly
and reversible
but still super useful
propositions
exactly and they actually they're
actually not computational completely
costly they would be if you were to
reject
many samples but here you in Hamilton
Monte Carlo typically you don't get to
reject many samples so yeah you that's
such a I mean that's such a great
picture see the card follows the shadow
Road by just doing geometric integration
and following the shadow hamiltonian
every once in a while you get a momentum
refreshment a little bit of Steel
refreshment which is oh um now I moved
to the first lane or the second main
third lane and so on and you get a
metropolis Hastings correction step that
tells that says do I accept this
proposition proposition proposal of Link
change or do I reject it and so on it
goes
so
how does this connect to active
inference
well I mean great question uh so
inactive imprints
in active interest proper you don't have
any sampling inactive imprints uh
whenever you want to scale active
inference to
implement it to solve any kind of
problem in the world you want to do
sampling because there's a lot of
computations that are not going to be
trackable otherwise
and so one
um one cool example is when it's in the
figure after this actually so
when you want to vote for any kind of
decision making inactive inference you
need to approximate
the expected free energy and system
uh no the one just before here
uh yeah perfect
um
so if you look at the second equation
there you get this minus log P of of an
action sequence equals expectation of
something this minus log p on the action
sequence is our notation in this paper
for the expected free energy
um
so the expected I mean you probably all
know this the expected humanity is given
by the expectation of something
now
um typically and when you have a very
high dimensional model which happens in
in most applications I would say you get
a very high dimensional
expectation what is an expectation an
expectation is an integral with respect
to a probability distribution
how do you compute expectations well you
do that through sampling or at least
sampling is the way to compute High
dimensional expectations that's the most
efficient in statistics and this is the
reason why
something is studied in statistics is
because that's how you solve these
problems I mean explore expectation just
come up everywhere
um just like so many things about
machine learning boil down to Computing
expectations and so
here in particular the expectation that
is very dear to to us very close to our
hearts is the one that gives you the
expected for energy the expected
frequency expectation of something so
how do you compute that in a high
dimensional model where you have to use
something
and so
there comes uh the usefulness of
hamiltonian Monte Carlo if you have a
discrete State space model you're now
going to be able to use simultaneous
Monte Carlo because hamiltonian Monte
Carlo is a continuous state-based models
um it's on continuous State space right
we talked about continuous positions
continuous velocity I talked about
sampling of probability distribution on
my desk
which is a continuous State space so
you're now going to be able to use
hamiltonian Monte Carlo if you have a
particularly observed Mark of decision
process when you're doing active
reference there where you have for
example I've been talking recently to
Ryan Smith
um who who does a lot of active
inference and and he's really leading a
lot of the modeling work with active
inference and real data of patients of
all sorts
many medical data and also using active
inference to model psychological
experiments and
um one of the things he told me about
well is okay well I have a bunch of data
and a partially observed marker decision
process is just not going to do it uh
why is it not gonna do it because the
data that he has is lives on a
continuous space I don't remember
exactly what it was but let's just say
for the sake of example that uh that
data was you know the temperature in the
room
and and people had to the the subjects
had to infer the temperature in the room
based on their Sensations
so that's a continuous database problem
now imagine that
you asked you asked someone to infer the
temperature in a room then maybe you
would change the temperature in the room
or not and you would ask them again
change the temperature or not and ask
them again and so on
in when you have this sort of setup you
have a discrete
you have a phenomenon that unfolds in
discrete time because you just
repeatedly ask some question and
sometimes elapses between the questions
um but you also have a state space
that's continuous when you have this
sort of data then the kind of model that
you want to use is a partially observed
markup decision process that like we
know and love but the state space is
going to be continuous instead of
discrete the time is still going to be
this week
um now when you have this sort of model
and I just want to say it as an or as a
yeah as an aside that for the moment a
lot of the modeling work and and
simulation work in active influence uses
the sweet State space on the piece
partially observed Mark of the same
process just because it's been
sufficient and when you simulate agent
is often like in green worlds and when
you maybe have a state spaces in
experiments they often buy design
discrete because just easier to handle
but that's not something that that's not
an assumption a simplifying assumption
that we're gonna have that we're going
to be able to keep or you know that much
longer there's just so many things that
you cannot account with these sort of
models so one other model that is
interesting to have is partially
observed Mark of decision process but
with A continuous State space
so with those you get the problem of you
know estimating the expected free energy
which would be then an expectation or in
other words an integration an integral
in a continuous State space and so how
do you do that efficiently if you are in
a high dimensional State space where you
use I'm not talking about the cardo I
think this would be really the the best
method so this is how you join the dots
um
in this paper we didn't talk about
um sampling in discrete space
because the methods are quite different
so we had we really had to choose what
to focus on there's a of course a lot
more methods in the literature than they
are in this paper we just wanted to sort
of review what were the main ones and
what people really used in practice
um
but you know when you have the expected
free energy in a discrete stated space
Computing the expectation
that defines the expected free energy
can often be a little bit easier because
it comes down computationally to a bunch
of Matrix multiplications
The Matrix Vector multiplications which
generally is doable unless I mean the
state phase is enormously high and then
we'd have to think of sampling methods
in this switch space
um but as soon as you move to a
partially observed markup decision
process in with A continuous space which
are iru and Ryan Smith argues and I'm
sure a lot of people have run into this
um as soon as you have this kind of
model
well yeah you just have an integration
problem in continuous space and so
Hamilton Monte Carlo is the way to go
there
awesome and your 2020 paper
was the synthesis on some of the
discrete State space
formalisms of active so it's very
interesting to see how you're now
talking about
where continuous time continuous State
spaces can come into play
and
how interesting that active inference
has uh
the capacity to deal with discrete and
continuous State spaces and sometimes we
lean on one leg or the other leg more
but it spans the Gap in a way that's
actually like a value adding not like
there's some sort of missing piece from
one side or the other
yeah yeah definitely I think active
information is great because it's so
flexible in the sort of models that you
can consider
um
but but yeah I mean
historically the first models to be
developed were continuous space and
continuous time
and then it works quite well because you
can take gradients of the free energy
and just minimize them over time
so you could you could get around
basically everything by doing a gradient
descent on free energy
and then after that around like so that
was like 2010 and then around 2015.
uh people started thinking okay well how
do I model
um discrete time decision making with
active inference
the
and typically
the decision-making task at least the
simple one that is studied in New York
Times in behavioral Neuroscience just to
make things simple
um the the number of actions that you
have is discrete so you have a family
number of actions you have also and
which is pretty small you would also
have a final number of dates which would
be pretty small and then and then people
started to think okay well how do we use
active reference to actually account for
that
um and so yeah and and so that's how the
whole expected free energy and partially
observed Mark of decision processes uh
came into play
and and now the community has grown a
lot and there's more and more data that
we want to account for there's more and
more projects that are going on
and where and you know people are
realizing and I think I mean it's an
obvious realization it's just not
um it's not surprising at all that these
two models developed in 2010 2015
they're just not going to account for
everything you need to think about other
kinds of models
and it really depends on what kind of
data you have at hand
and then one important and obvious type
of model would be partially observed
Mark of decision process with continuous
space and actually this is not a new
thing I mean people have been using
these kind of models um in reinforcement
learning and control for a long time
I don't know to what extent they've
arrived at practically I mean big Fair
arrived at practically implementable
algorithms I don't know to what extent
they're used to what extend their state
of the art
um but the point is they it's something
that it's a kind of model that you know
has existed for a long time
um and so this
sampling is would be a way to actually
practically implement this and scale it
when you want to put that within active
inference so I think yeah it's an
important thing is just think about
awesome yeah Thomas Parr also recently
in a discussion on the textbook was
sharing some timelines and it's just so
interesting how these things have been
developing and from continuous through
characterization of the discrete
in a sense not culminating but being
synthesized in your 2020 paper and now
there's with an increased emphasis on
empirical data
the desire to bring in a lot of these
methods that actually help us implement
it rather than just think about it
really parsimoniously so
what is your
active inference
representation in the figure of the
running person
and then how do the variables and the
processes described in this figure
relate to all of this you know five
hours of talking about Shadow
hamiltonians and all of this
really
um yeah that's a broad question we might
need another 10 hours you know to 10 so
then detail but uh just very short
um
well so the active inference section was
meant to be as complete as possible even
though it was very short and by complete
by completeness I mean that we started
by deriving active inference and
deriving active inference for first
principles
um so this is really what the free
energy principle does even though we
weren't able of course to you know
review the whole free energy principle
in like one or two pages but we
what we focused on was deriving the
expected reality from first principles
and then from there you get the full
active inference algorithm so proactive
Infamous algorithm I think you just went
past it is just below
um if you go slightly below I think
maybe patient nine or page 30 yeah uh
still I think next yeah realizing an
active agents yeah so this is the
difference algorithm like
0.1 2.3 or something so just from a
duration of the expected free energy
um you actually get as a corollary from
there the active inference algorithm
that we know and love this is actually a
more General version than what people
use
and I'd be excited and I'm actually
talking to people to actually Implement
that
um but this is actually the most General
version that has been established in the
literature
and it is more generally the meaningful
way in the sense that all the beliefs
all the probability distributions they
are over trajectories or sequences of
events so it's not only so so it means
that all the computations
they not only consider events at a
particular
time in the future for example but they
consider trajectories of sequences of
events and so
this is equivalent to considering
different events at different points in
time and their kind of independencies
and dependencies between them
um so this is just to say that if you
take if you would take then this
algorithm and you wouldn't perform a
mean-shield approximation over time
which is uh saying that all the things
that you see in the future are sort of
independent of each other at different
points in time
then you would recover what people
typically use in in the literature which
is easily implementable the the point I
want to make here is that you can
actually not have that limitation and
have things that are a bit more
um
yeah a bit more complex that are able to
capture more complex relationships in
the time series and input that they
might be receiving like the kind of
sensory data that they might be
receiving and the kind of genitive
models that they would have
uh so anyway this is the active
inference algorithm the most General one
and we derived that from first
principles by deriving the expected
Community from first principles and so
this relates us to to that figure that
you just showed so that that figure that
you showed
um with s o a is the starting point of
the free energy Principle as it's
described in this paper and so the point
is that the world the point that we want
to describe decision making
uh went to describe actions as the
function of Sensations
and so and we want to come up with the
most General description of
actions as a function of Sensations to
be able to account for everything that's
kind of the idea of the pre-enter
principle
um so what do we do is we consider a
world
a world in which there is an environment
and an agent and so the environment here
is denoted by S and S is a stochastic
process what is stochastic process
um because a stoopathic process is the
most General type of dynamic that exists
at least as far as I know
um it's really a random Dynamic and it
could be random in all sorts of ways it
could also be done random we sort of
take the the stochastic the random
aspect as the extra ingredient just to
include a lot more types of scenarios
and things you can be confronted with so
if you partition the world into the
agent which is O and A
and the environment which is s and the
agent then you subdivided into two more
components which are o and a o are the
what we call the observable state so
these are like the sensations of the
observations that you get at any point
in time also a stochastic practice
and finally you have the autonomous
States or you could think about it
Loosely as the active States they turn
out to be the active states in the
implementation but so the active dates
they're really
um you know like the muscles the things
you can actually activate and make it
and then activate to you know influence
the world
um so we just partition the world into
these three sets of states that interact
and and evolve in some way they're both
really stochastic processes and in that
interact and then the goal of the
community principle at least when
applied to decision making is that you
want to describe a as a function of o
because what so what happens as an
organism you can you have control over a
you have access to O but you don't have
Direct Control of o or your Sensations
and you don't have access to S because
that's the environment and beyond beyond
the markup like it Beyond view beyond
your envelope so you don't have access
to as you know o and you can control a a
is what you can choose from and so the
300 principle just answers the question
okay well
um if I take this very general
description of the world
how
what is the equation of a as a function
of O how can I describe a as a function
of o
and so it turns out
um there's some mild assumptions in this
and these assumptions uh they're they're
Guided by physical considerations about
how humans
are and how humans interact with the
world but they're very meld but whenever
you take these assumptions you get that
the active States or the autonomous
States minimize expected free energy
so so this is like a very succinct
um derivation of the expected free
energy from first principles we start
with the partition of the world we
describe active States as a function of
observations and so it turns out that
the expected free energy is what
describes the active States as a
function of observations
um
and so
and and so the basic active inference
algorithm which everybody uses and which
we have proposed in the paper is about
it's all about Computing the expected
free energy and then selecting actions
that minimizes expected free energy
so the expected for the energy as we saw
I think it's in the next figure so the
one with all the panels
well within it a couple times already
it's um it's an expectation with
posterior distributions in it
um
what I mean by posterior distributions
here is that these are distributions
conditioned on the history of the agent
so in the observation that he has
already seen and on the actions that he
has already taken
in any case
in any case we have the expected free
energy is an expectation with posterior
distributions within so it means that to
compute the expected free energy you
have two problems you have Computing
posterior distributions through Bayesian
inference base Rule and you then once
you have them you can plug them in into
this equation and then you you need to
complete the expectation
and then you get the expected view
energy so the first thing is about
Computing the posterior distributions
now what has been proposed in the
literature so far is well how do you do
approximate inference how do you
actually approximate distributions you
do that through variational imprints or
approximate inference by minimizing
fluidity
then
the treatment here the derivation and we
our aim was to do the provided
derivation that was as conceptually
simple as possible actually it
highlights that the free energy is not
the most important thing here
um the important thing is really the
expected free energy the free energy is
just a tool to approximate the posterior
distributions to then get the expected
energy but you could actually use any
other type of Divergence the community
is just like a tail Divergent plus some
term that makes the whole thing
tractable and so you can minimize the
Cal Divergence to approximate the
targeted distribution but actually what
what this view highlights and by the way
I'm not at all against the free energy I
think it's really cool and whenever and
there's so many methods to minimize free
energy and if you can do that then fine
and sure go for it like way to go but
imagine you could not do that it would
not at all be a problem because you
could use any other kind of Divergence
to solve those inference problems
um so so that would be the first step
you're going to approximate those
posterior distributions by doing some
kind of approximate inference which
would be through minimization of the
energy or the minimization of something
else
and then you have the Second Step which
is Computing the expectation now either
you're in a
low number of states discrete States
probably P like thing and it's all a
matter of vector Matrix multiplications
that are attractable
either you have a very very high number
of discrete States and then you need to
think about sampling
um in discrete states which we didn't
discuss in this paper either you are in
a continuous database and then you have
an expectation in continuous State space
and then you want to think about an
alternate Monte Carlo for example
so now with these two steps you have now
an estimate of the expected free energy
which gives you the quality of any
action sequence
and so it's not only the quality rates
actually the negative log probability of
any action sequence regarding in this
formalism because if you remember the
you know the premise of all this was to
describe actions as functional
Sensations in a physical system in not
even a physical system but in
interacting stochastic processes
[Music]
um
and so the answer to that was well the
expected energy gives us you know gives
us how actions relate to Sensations
um the expected humanity and this is why
we use the letter we usually we used
minus log P of the a as opposed to G to
emphasize that the expected free energy
is not just like a function of oxygen
sequences but it is
really the negative log probability of
an action sequence given some Sensations
um and so once you have computed the
expected free energy you had this minus
log probability of an action sequence
if you take the exponential negative of
that the exponential negative of the
expected free energy you get
um you get the probability distribution
over action sequences
um
and so by the way this exponential
negative of expected frequentity is what
we use all the time you might recognize
this as the sub Max of negative expected
free energy this is just all the time
um kind of fundamental thing in active
influence models so really talking about
the same thing here
um
so once you take the soft Max of
negative expected free energy you get P
of a which is the distribution of
reaction sequences and now you have two
possibilities
either you want to stimulate the most
likely action sequence in which case
you want to simulate the the actual
sequence that maximizes the probability
distribution
um so in effect you have an optimization
problem you out of all
um yeah you need to find the action
sequence that is going to maximize this
probability distribution that's given by
the expected free energy
or
um or you want to simulate a typical
action so what do I mean a typical
action a typical action or a typical
action sequence is just a sample from
the distribution
and so if you want to sample from
I mean if you want to do that then you
have a sampling problem or again you
need to sample from from a distribution
over action sequences given by the
expected free energy
so this is really how how all these
methodologies connect
um
yeah I think
I think that's kind of it yeah one last
thing is
um typically when we stimulate active
inference we never do the sampling at
the end we always take the action
sequence that minimizes expected reality
in other words in other words the action
sequence that maximizes that probability
distribution
um and this is because when we simulate
things we it turns out I mean this is
how people have done it in the
literature people are more interested in
the most likely action sequence that
um that an organism or an agent would
produce but if you want to model data if
you want to use active inference to
model data then you actually want to not
just simulate the most likely action
sequence but simulate
any kind of action sequence that would
fall out of this and so this is really
the case where you need to sample from
that final distribution as opposed to
the optimization
so depending on the use case you either
have a sampling or an optimization
problem
after you've
um you've computed the expected free
energy so this is how these whole Things
Fall together and and so you might be
asking okay well you talked about
sampling and optimization there's also a
section about inference where does that
fit in and so it fits in to
uh it fits in on on the remark I gave
that you know we have this posterior
distributions within the expected
fragility how do we compute them how do
we approximate them one way is by
minimizing free energy another way is by
minimizing any other kind of Divergence
and in that section over there we just
reviewed some kind of divergences that
are very popular in the in this school
in Prince literature mainly because they
have desirable properties
and and so if you weren't able
um to use the variation of the energy
for some reason or maybe something to be
explored and something to be explored is
just to use another type other types of
divergences and and just see what
happens
um
so the the open problem to be explored
is whether we can get better performance
by using different kinds of divergences
and and see what we get
uh maybe there's particle algorithms
that are out there with these other
types of diverges then we can make use
of to do better performance
to get better performance can we
actually describe and quantify the
improvements in performance that we get
by using these other types of algorithms
when would these be appropriate and
useful and these are all open questions
um another good question that I think is
interesting is can we model maladaptive
Behavior
by using different kinds of divergences
that would not work as well as the free
energy
and this um there's an interesting paper
on that by uh newer Sajid
I think and colleagues I think it's
called um
Bayesian brain Basin brains and the
Rainy Divergence it's been published in
neural computation
I think last year or the year before and
answering that paper instead of using
the variation of free energy to
approximate all these posterior
distributions
um she used the Rainy Divergence which
is
which generalizes the kale Divergence in
some way and show that for different
rainy divergences you got different
types of approximate posteriors and she
basically
looked into yeah what kind of
differences you get from there in terms
of perception in terms of decision
making and she showed that for that
particular diver
gence I think the conclusion was that
you basically get different
phenomenology you get different Behavior
suggest something to be explored I think
the upshot was that maybe
I I don't remember how far the paper
went in this but I think kind of the the
goal was to model maladaptive Behavior
using some kinds of rainy divergences
that did not work as well as the free
energy
so this is to say so this is an
interesting work
um one could examine other kinds of
divergences and see whether you actually
get better or worse performance than
with the free energy
uh one thing one word of caution though
is the ex the free energy is
it's just so good in the sense that it
uses the KL Divergence
and as I mentioned at the beginning the
care Librarians has so many properties
and it's just so fundamental
um it's not straightforward to see that
when you first come up with it but I
guess the more I read
in different disciplines and the more
the kale the evidence comes up and the
more the more I see properties of Cal
Divergence in different disciplines that
just make it so interesting like for
example the kale emergency in
statistical physics is the relative
entropy so
quantifies the amount of entropy that a
distribution has with respect to another
entropy as we know is just a very
fundamental thing in information Theory
the KL Divergence quantifies the
difference in information between two
distributions the amount of bits that
you will need to
I mean
um
if you take two distributions A and B
the KL between the two
quantifies the amount of information
that it takes to go from one to the
other so now you might object and say
okay but klanb is different from KL BNA
and so how can it be that
you know it quantifies the amount of
information
um they need to go from A to B or B to a
because it's not symmetric
um so the answer is
it's either KL of A and B of A and B
that has this meaning or KL of DNA that
has this meaning and I just can never
remember which direction it's one of
them that has this interpretation in
terms of
the difference in information
anyway
um so kale is just like um something it
just comes up everywhere and it's just
um so useful and it has all of these
nice properties which makes these free
energy really a construct of choice
but that said there's other divergences
one of them which we describe a bit in
the paper called um the maximum mean
discrepancy which I think also has nice
properties it's not necessarily
well it's a bit different it's very
different in terms of how you construct
it from the kale Divergence but I think
my current understanding right now and
um my current understanding right now is
that if you cannot use KL then maximum
mean discrepancy is just like be nice
but but yeah so the word of question was
that probably most divergences out there
are not gonna do as good of a job as a
free energy uh but some clever ones
might
and it's an open problem of you know
determining which
and and yeah so this is how you know we
get the link between all these different
sections so to
to do perception we need the inference
to do decision making that is Computing
the expected free energy we need
sampling
typically and then to do action
selection we either need sampling or
optimization and also inference is
an optimization of beliefs and sampling
of that we as we've discussed is also an
optimization of probability
distributions you can see that as an
optimization of beliefs as well so it's
all very tightly interconnected
wow thank you Lance that's very
informative
brings up a lot of
ways to go
and it it really shines a different
light on even what learning active
inference or learning free energy
principle it was a roller coaster just
listening
when
you describe the figure of the running
person
and the new generalized
representation here which is so sparse
it looks like it's pseudocode but it's
actually basically necessary and
sufficient
to describe
yeah it is pseudocode and it is also
exact like this is really what active
influence boils down to and that was
kind of like where we got it we're like
okay well we have this mass of papers of
active inference and that they're
actually a mess but you know there's so
much information
and we're you know really thinking
reading all this the latest free energy
principle literature that I've also
worked on a lot and also the active in
French literature and really thinking
okay well how do we strip all that of
the Neuroscience how do we strip all
that of the cognitive science how do we
just retain the math and present it in
the simplest way possible that would be
appealing for a mathematician and also
hopefully for a computer scientist
it turns out that we got a way simpler
perspective than anything that's out
there I think
um and really yeah so this is the active
inference algorithm
in studio code and in detail also in in
a way
so I totally agree again thanks for the
work and for sharing it this way because
it is the fewest pixels
for the highest resolution picture
so
then to describe the
fundamental cybernetic challenge
as a partition
an axiomatic partition which one can
then say also has grounding in the
spatial temporal boundaries of the world
or in geometric boundaries in
informational spaces but the particular
partition is used to separate
um
in the map
not necessarily making claims about the
territory and the actual nature of the
objects and their articulations or
Anatomy but on the map which we get to
construct
we make it in a way that's amenable to
the particular partition which is not
too much more than the separation of
figure from ground or agent-based
modeling it's just a separation of some
autonomous entity from some external
process
then the task of the free energy
principle applied to decision making as
you said was to describe action as a
function of observation
and everything in between
is broadly considered cognitive
but for any given system it's going to
play out in this immensely nuanced way
with a lot of bespoke mechanisms
and why do we take that particular
partition step
well
it's kind of like read write access in a
computer system there's things we don't
have access to Hidden States
and also the reverse of that which is we
can't access hidden States nor them
influence or affect us so I think of
that as like no telekinesis no telepathy
you can't go directly across the blanket
you have to intermediate through the
blanket of observation action and then
with respect to our particular States
our blanket and internal States we have
access to observations but not Direct
Control nor necessarily would we want to
because if we had the lever to change
what we directly received then
algorithms might learn strategies that
basically self-deceive so that the
observations look good look good look
good until the whole system crashes so
we want access to observations but not
Direct Control and then the autonomous
states are what we in the optimal ideal
situation have total control of which is
like our mind and our body what we think
and what we do
it turns out
through the pragmatic turn and the
inactivist insights in cognitive science
that a lot of action sequences have to
do with changing What observations are
sought after like epistemic affordances
so there is an enmeshment of action but
it's also really important that we have
access but not control of observations
we don't want to have like our control
on the thermometer but we want the best
possible thermometer and then we want to
control the best possible interpretation
that's like signal processing and the
best possible action sequence which is
like decision making and control theory
and then free energy principle is
addressing that question what is the
equation
of action as a function of observation
but then it was quite a roller coaster
when you said that the free energy
wasn't even necessarily the only way to
do it but it's absolutely true it's yeah
the properties of the free energy are
inherited from one of the terms being
the KL Divergence any other having the
ability to basically ignore in certain
relative expected free energy
calculation contexts so then in that
situation differences in free energy do
come down to differences in the KL which
does have all these properties but that
doesn't mean that the free energy is
itself axiomatically posited
it's actually Downstream of the
particular partition to use free energy
or anything like that at all and other
discrepancies may have other properties
in different ways
exactly and and so there's a bit of a
Nuance in the sense that here we
presented this version of the advantage
principle just describing decision
making as you as you summarize the
describing a as a function of O
um but if we
and and by the way about that so we're
we didn't even talk about Marco blanket
in this paper
um I would I would say that the mark of
blanket is under the hood because we're
saying okay well these are the states
that you have access to and these are
the states that you do not the states
that you have access to are a and o the
states of the agent and it states that
you do not have access to your ID
environment so in some sense
there is a markup blanket but we didn't
even mention we didn't even have to
mention that in the paper it's just you
partition the world into three sets of
States as o a
um that are by definition a
um and you just yeah just from this
tripartition you want to describe one as
a function of another ignoring the Third
um and so that yeah that how you derive
expected Community you see that action
sequences are described by the expected
for energy and these this is a function
of Sensations
um if we weren't very there in the and
so this is just what you need crucially
this is just what you need to derive the
active inference algorithm if you if we
went further in reviewing the free
energy principle then we would see the
fundamental role that the free energy
plays
um
and so actually when you know reading
the latest papers on the mathematical
theory of the community principle the
role of the variation of the energy is
pretty clear
but here the point is that if we just
care about decision making if we just
care about the normal active inference
algorithm then we don't even need the
variation of free energy so sure the
community should be preferred why not if
it is available but if it is not for
some reason then there's no reason why
not to use another kind of Divergence
so
very interesting it's making me think
about linear regression
and the sum of squares the L2 Norm is
one approach that's often used to fit a
regression line because it has good
optimization properties there's good
software packages there's good education
there's good communication around it and
so on but one can select other norms
and choose to fit a linear regression
with an L1 Norm or with an L3 Norm
and so
that
entire question of fitting the linear
regression
is a degree of Freedom how the
regression is fit
that's Downstream of a commitment to for
example Model A system in a generalized
linear modeling framework
and so analogously the Upstream
commitment or the first principles which
yes can be understood as axiomatic and
also have some empirical status in terms
of this partitioning a figure from
ground the particular partition can
simply be accepted axiomatically which
is to say without appeal to evidence or
somebody might have another Upstream
Axiom and choose to model things
according to a particular partition
from there just like we could have
chosen the l123 norm
there are different
discrepancy criteria
or measures
that we might want to use
and some of them apply better or worse
or not at all
depending on what software Hardware
data set and generative model we have
and so it makes sense to pull pull back
into the the Upstream understanding
of active inference as a process Theory
for particular partitioned systems
and then for those who want to engage in
the modeling
to have that
uh discussion about the garden of the
branching paths well you could use a
discrete timer you could use a
continuous time and then from here you
could do this sampling or you could do
that one and if we have this computer
access we can do that but if we have to
do it this way we'll do it like that
and that's all operational and
logistical but it's actually
all under the umbrella or under the
auspice of the theoretical or conceptual
commitments that are actually not being
questioned once one is in that modeling
discussion just like you could have the
l123 norm conversation and maybe a
reviewer asks you why you chose the two
Norm versus the three but it's a broader
level of questioning
why one took on the linear modeling
framework at all and our analogous
Upstream bottleneck
not in terms of rate limiting but just
in terms of like eye of the needle is
the particular partition
yeah definitely and I just want to add
something actually about the choice of
divergences or the choice of discrepancy
that you might want to use to solve the
inference problem I think the analogy
with linear regression is a really good
one when you delay in your regression
yeah you can use all types of norms and
it's really a design choice and here in
the algorithm you you also have that
design Choice are you going to use KL so
free energy
to do these inferences
by the way the inferences are really
equation
43 and 44 which are approximate
um actually you had them in a slide
already
OH 43 and 44 oh oh here got it yeah yeah
um which are approximate
um you know some posterior distribution
with an approximate per serial
distribution so you can do that with the
free energy which is the same as the KL
Divergence or you could do that with a
whole bunch of other divergences one
that I mentioned and that I think is
particularly interesting is the maximum
mean discrepancy and so
um here's the difference between KL and
maximum heat discrepancy at least like I
guess a important conceptual difference
so the KL when you look at distributions
that are very close to each other it's
going to measure it's basically going to
become symmetric when when the
distributions are very close and it's
going to measure the amount of
information
uh that differs between them the maximum
mean discrepancy when you take two
distributions that are very close it's
gonna
it it reduces to what people call the
Earth movers distance also called like
the Vassar time distance so here is the
intuition if you take two distributions
that are very close just imagine the
solution a as a backup dirt and
distribution b as a pack of dirt or or a
stand with some shape the maximum mean
discrepancy is gonna
tell you the amount of work
that you need to put all that dirt from
distribution a and pile it in the shape
of distribution B so of course there's
so many different ways in in which you
could take all that dirt from
distribution a and remodel it in
distribution B but you're interested in
the minimal
um the minimal energetic cost that we
take so like the optimal way of doing
that movement people call that optimal
transport
um now if you're if you're familiar with
optimal transport you know that the
faster time distance
um is the distance between probability
distributions that regardless of how far
they are
is going to measure
um
like the it is going to give you this um
cost of optimal transport so the
energetic cost of moving all that
um you know a pack of dirt from place a
to place B in the optimal way
um so the investors time distance is
something that we could use here
but maximum mean discrepancy it has a
lot of very nice properties and
basically reduces to the Watson distance
when we consider very close
distributions so
uh this is not something that just a
mathematical curiosity but it says that
when one build when one builds a
distance out of a Divergence what one
does is one takes you know very close
distributions measures the Divergence
between them at which point the
Divergence is pretty much symmetrical
and then you basically keep adding
divergences along a trajectory until you
get to the final one and this way by
aggregating divergences between very
close distributions
I'm doing that and you know adding that
along a trajectory you get a distance a
meaningful distance between you know
distributions that could be very far
if you do that with the KL Divergence
you get What's called the Fischer
information distance which measures
really the
um
really um yeah the the amount of
information that took you from gold
to go from one distribution to another
distribution regardless of how far they
are
um if you do that with advanced search
time distance you will get the optimal
transport cost so the amount of energy
that you need to put all that dirt
please say to place me in the optimal
way if you do that with the maximum
discrepancy you would also get that you
will also get the optimal transport
thing so
um I just so the yeah I just want to say
that the maximum discrepancy mean
discrepancy between two distributions
that are far away or not coincide with
the vast search time distance which
gives you this optimal transport cost
but when you actually derive a distance
from these divergences the distance
derived from the maximum discrepancy and
the Western distance will end up being
the same
and um
this distance that you actually get or
the topology
that is derived from the distance so by
topology the topology is really a notion
of closeness
and so to understand closeness you need
to understand you know intestinal
distances
um so the infinitesimal distances
derived from vassarstein or MMD they're
the same
and the topology that results is the
topology of what people call weak
convergence which is the standard
topology that's considered in a
probability Theory
um
so MMD and investors time they are very
natural in that sense in the sense that
they
they uh they people say that they match
rise weak conversions like they give
give rise to the standard topology
between probability distributions
um
so coming back to the choice of
divergences if you're interested in
approximating distributions in the sense
of approximating their information
content then KL is very natural but if
it was for some reason and maybe would
not be in this kind of application but
another kind of application if for some
reason you're interested in
approximating distributions for the sake
of how close they are when you look at
them
then then you would use MMD or Vassar
shine
wow great
great information
and I'm just thinking about
we're switching lanes on the highway
we're trying to get from here to there
yes we want to know about the
informational closeness of this Tale of
Two densities but we also want to know
about the transport closeness because we
have a schedule and a budget and
decisions to make and there are
trade-offs so being able to move the
Earth
optimally while we're switching lanes
and accelerating and slowing down
I know this is mixing many angles
informally
we want to have a lot of options
for how to think about that challenge of
moving dirt between the tale of two
densities
and make sure everybody is driving in
the right lane at the right time
definitely and yeah it's a it's a design
choice and it's an important one because
it depends on you know what kind of
properties we want to preserve
and yes so all these all these
divergences some some are not so useful
I guess but um some of them they're
they're just very natural and the
Western and mme they're very natural in
that sense
um so yeah very important to keep in
mind and not only for active inference
but just you know in general
uh for any kind of interest from them
well let us each have a closing round of
Reflections any
thoughts
or any next steps or any suggestions or
other information you'd like to provide
it's hard to say I feel we've you know
we've covered so much already
um
there's still I think to me what's most
exciting about is a scaling active
inference right now
um because you know you get this active
interest algorithm in the paper uh
that's derived from first principles and
just from the derivation you see okay
well there's actually so many things I
mean the assumptions are so small that
there are so many things that you can
model with this active reference
algorithm and
basically you oh and all the heavy
lifting is done by the genital model
so if you use one relative model you
will get one Behavior if you use another
jointed model you will get another
Behavior but all the equations will
remain the same
um so so it speaks the generality now in
in having something that's very general
you get something that's also very
non-specific
and I guess for for neuroscientists and
people who are interested in
intelligence you just
um generality comes at a cost of being
you know non-specific and non-specific
about the brain in general
um so really the big question to me uh
long term is what kind of genitive
models do we need to simulate brain-like
Behavior because this is really the
interesting Behavior or the most
interesting Behavior
um so it speaks to a big research
program that a lot of people are
carrying and have been carrying for a
long time but you know
um it's about what kind of
representations do we have of the world
what kind of priors do we have what kind
of uh can we identify the priors that we
are born with there's a lot of research
on
computational or just plain concrete
science like normal cognitive science
just studying babies and seeing what
kind of priors what kind of you know
basic information they have when they
come out of the womb there's a lot of
things that they can already do there
our genetic code is preconditioning us
to operate efficiently in this world and
be able to flexibly adapt to any kind of
situations that might arise in the
natural world and so it's a huge
research program to you know understand
and model these priors and
um
yeah and not only the prayers but also
the likelihood all the representation
all the state spaces
uh so I think that's the way forward the
community principle is very elegant
because it gives you you know a very
succinct description in terms of a giant
and model that enables you to simulate
pretty much everything but we're not
interested in simulating anything we're
interested in simulating brain-like
behaviors so now we need to you know
drill down even more onto the kind of
genetic models that that would be
amenable to that
great
my closing reflection
I feel like I know less about fep
more about something else for what we've
discussed
Earth was moved
Bayesian mechanics were called in
decisions were made
and it's been a really great Series so
I'm appreciative and thankful that you
suggested this paper
in our correspondence as one to discuss
you were absolutely right that it is
relevant to bring to the attention of
the active community
and
I hope that everybody
who reads or listens this far
has
shifted Lanes so they can be where they
want to be too
well that yeah I mean uh thank you so
much I also really enjoyed this session
and I think we had a really cool
discussion
um so thanks again and hope to do this
again soon
excellent anytime you'd like
farewell
sealance there's
thank you